<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://digitalgarden.hypha.coop/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://digitalgarden.hypha.coop/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-07-27T15:10:20+02:00</updated><id>https://digitalgarden.hypha.coop/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Digital Garden | Notes</title><subtitle>A digital garden or public notebook for The Bentway’s Digital and/as Public Space Micro-Residency.</subtitle><author><name>Hypha Worker Co-operative</name></author><entry><title type="html">Climate Reporting</title><link href="https://digitalgarden.hypha.coop/climate-reporting" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Climate Reporting" /><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-07-26T14:58:15+02:00</updated><id>https://digitalgarden.hypha.coop/Climate%20Reporting</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://digitalgarden.hypha.coop/climate-reporting">&lt;p&gt;INTRO&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;open-questions&quot;&gt;Open Questions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;TBA&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;further-reading&quot;&gt;Further Reading&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.systems.journalismdesign.com/modules&quot;&gt;A toolkit for reporting on complex problems – J+D&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Journalism + Design has developed a suite of systems thinking tools for journalists to focus their reporting on the underlying causes of complex problems: the policies, power dynamics, and beliefs fueling systems that actively harm, marginalize, or benefit specific people.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;</content><author><name>Hypha Worker Co-operative</name></author><summary type="html">INTRO Open Questions TBA Further Reading A toolkit for reporting on complex problems – J+D Journalism + Design has developed a suite of systems thinking tools for journalists to focus their reporting on the underlying causes of complex problems: the policies, power dynamics, and beliefs fueling systems that actively harm, marginalize, or benefit specific people.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Auto—Augmentation</title><link href="https://digitalgarden.hypha.coop/auto-augmentation" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Auto—Augmentation" /><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-07-26T14:58:28+02:00</updated><id>https://digitalgarden.hypha.coop/Auto%E2%80%94Augmentation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://digitalgarden.hypha.coop/auto-augmentation"></content><author><name>Hypha Worker Co-operative</name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ad-Tech Mess</title><link href="https://digitalgarden.hypha.coop/ad-tech-mess" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ad-Tech Mess" /><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-07-26T15:00:44+02:00</updated><id>https://digitalgarden.hypha.coop/Ad-Tech%20Mess</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://digitalgarden.hypha.coop/ad-tech-mess">&lt;p&gt;INTRO&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;open-questions&quot;&gt;Open Questions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;TBA&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;further-reading&quot;&gt;Further Reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-TBA&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;QUOTE&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Hypha Worker Co-operative</name></author><summary type="html">INTRO Open Questions TBA Further Reading -TBA QUOTE</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">New Local Media</title><link href="https://digitalgarden.hypha.coop/new-local-media" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Local Media" /><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-07-26T14:59:24+02:00</updated><id>https://digitalgarden.hypha.coop/New%20Local%20Media</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://digitalgarden.hypha.coop/new-local-media">&lt;p&gt;Light local media are outlets build around a newsletter and a small core team of writers with minimal overhead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;examples&quot;&gt;Examples&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://patch.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Patch&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; — A network of newsletters written by local reporters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;open-questions&quot;&gt;Open Questions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;TBA&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;further-reading&quot;&gt;Further Reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.niemanlab.org/2019/10/from-newsroom-to-newsletter-how-local-journalists-are-diying-important-coverage-via-email/?relatedstory&quot;&gt;From newsroom to newsletter: How local journalists are DIYing important coverage via email – Nieman Journalism Lab&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This is more than 40 hours a week for far less than minimum wage. To be frank, it’s exhausting. I only do it because it’s so important,” Boulder Beat’s Castle told me hours after a city council meeting had wrapped up around midnight. “It’s weird being the only voice, the only one. You have no backup.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;</content><author><name>Hypha Worker Co-operative</name></author><summary type="html">Light local media are outlets build around a newsletter and a small core team of writers with minimal overhead. Examples Patch — A network of newsletters written by local reporters Open Questions TBA Further Reading From newsroom to newsletter: How local journalists are DIYing important coverage via email – Nieman Journalism Lab This is more than 40 hours a week for far less than minimum wage. To be frank, it’s exhausting. I only do it because it’s so important,” Boulder Beat’s Castle told me hours after a city council meeting had wrapped up around midnight. “It’s weird being the only voice, the only one. You have no backup.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Internet Futures</title><link href="https://digitalgarden.hypha.coop/internet-futures" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Internet Futures" /><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-07-26T15:23:31+02:00</updated><id>https://digitalgarden.hypha.coop/Internet%20Futures</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://digitalgarden.hypha.coop/internet-futures">&lt;h3 id=&quot;corp-nets&quot;&gt;Corp-Nets&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;splinternets&quot;&gt;Splinternets&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arguably there was never anything akin to a truly “world wide web”. The experience of the internet has always been shaped by local laws, language, available plattforms and service-providers. The idea of splinternets carries this experience a step further by describing almost completely closed-off networks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One prominent exmple is the Chinese internet, which is almost impossible to leave from within China, also dubbed “the great firewall”. A more tame example, though, might be the European internet. Through legislation such as the GDPR certain American businesses decided to block European users from their services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;web3&quot;&gt;Web3&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;open-questions&quot;&gt;Open Questions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;TBA&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;further-reading&quot;&gt;Further Reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-TBA&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;QUOTE&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Hypha Worker Co-operative</name></author><summary type="html">Corp-Nets Splinternets Arguably there was never anything akin to a truly “world wide web”. The experience of the internet has always been shaped by local laws, language, available plattforms and service-providers. The idea of splinternets carries this experience a step further by describing almost completely closed-off networks. One prominent exmple is the Chinese internet, which is almost impossible to leave from within China, also dubbed “the great firewall”. A more tame example, though, might be the European internet. Through legislation such as the GDPR certain American businesses decided to block European users from their services. Web3 Open Questions TBA Further Reading -TBA QUOTE</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Infrastructure</title><link href="https://digitalgarden.hypha.coop/infrastructure" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Infrastructure" /><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-07-26T15:13:50+02:00</updated><id>https://digitalgarden.hypha.coop/Infrastructure</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://digitalgarden.hypha.coop/infrastructure">&lt;p&gt;https://www.vice.com/en/article/qj8xz3/a-defunct-video-hosting-site-is-flooding-normal-websites-with-hardcore-porn?utm_source=motherboard_twitter&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;social-infrastructure&quot;&gt;Social Infrastructure&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With social media plattforms and search engines facilitating a big part of the interaction between a publisher and its audience, news organizations arguably have no control over how and where there content gets delivered online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And even in the best cases this relationship favors positioning and power of the platform, while shaping the rules of said relationship. A famous example of the changing rules might be the “pivot to video” by &lt;em&gt;Facebook&lt;/em&gt;—a strategy change by the company towards more video content in its feeds. Through botched numbers and a prominent PR-campaign the company build a mirage of possible higher ad-revenues prompting publishers to lay-off writers in favor of video reporters. A critical mistake since &lt;em&gt;Facebook&lt;/em&gt; didn’t deliver on the promised returns, resulting in a second wave of lay-offs and even closures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is just on example of what I’ve come to call &lt;a class=&quot;internal-link&quot; href=&quot;/the-algorithm&quot;&gt;The Algorithm&lt;/a&gt;—a stand-in for the number of algorithms and systems shaping the output, strategy and structure of publishers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;advertising-infrastructure&quot;&gt;Advertising Infrastructure&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;internal-link&quot; href=&quot;/ad-tech-mess&quot;&gt;Ad-Tech Mess&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;internet-futures&quot;&gt;Internet Futures&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;internal-link&quot; href=&quot;/internet-futures&quot;&gt;Internet Futures&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;open-questions&quot;&gt;Open Questions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;TBA&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;further-reading&quot;&gt;Further Reading&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;</content><author><name>Hypha Worker Co-operative</name></author><summary type="html">https://www.vice.com/en/article/qj8xz3/a-defunct-video-hosting-site-is-flooding-normal-websites-with-hardcore-porn?utm_source=motherboard_twitter Social Infrastructure With social media plattforms and search engines facilitating a big part of the interaction between a publisher and its audience, news organizations arguably have no control over how and where there content gets delivered online. And even in the best cases this relationship favors positioning and power of the platform, while shaping the rules of said relationship. A famous example of the changing rules might be the “pivot to video” by Facebook—a strategy change by the company towards more video content in its feeds. Through botched numbers and a prominent PR-campaign the company build a mirage of possible higher ad-revenues prompting publishers to lay-off writers in favor of video reporters. A critical mistake since Facebook didn’t deliver on the promised returns, resulting in a second wave of lay-offs and even closures. This is just on example of what I’ve come to call [[The Algorithm]]—a stand-in for the number of algorithms and systems shaping the output, strategy and structure of publishers. Advertising Infrastructure [[Ad-Tech Mess]] Internet Futures [[Internet Futures]] Open Questions TBA Further Reading</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Indie-Journalism</title><link href="https://digitalgarden.hypha.coop/indie-journalism" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Indie-Journalism" /><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-07-26T14:59:56+02:00</updated><id>https://digitalgarden.hypha.coop/Indie-Journalism</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://digitalgarden.hypha.coop/indie-journalism">&lt;p&gt;The “journalist as entrepreneur” is the latest way for journalists to go “indie”, i.e. monetizing their work not through a publisher but directly through a paying audience. This move has become increasingly easy through plattforms such as &lt;em&gt;Patreon&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Memberfull&lt;/em&gt; or newsletter plattforms such as  &lt;em&gt;Substack&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Revue&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though, as noted in &lt;a class=&quot;internal-link&quot; href=&quot;/influencer-journalists&quot;&gt;Influencer—Journalists&lt;/a&gt; this move has the possibility of compromising the image and credibility of journalists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A form of entrepreneurial journalism is also the emergence of &lt;a class=&quot;internal-link&quot; href=&quot;/new-local-media&quot;&gt;New Local Media&lt;/a&gt;. Small local outlets build often involving minimal overhead, small teams and a focus on digital media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;open-questions&quot;&gt;Open Questions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;further-reading&quot;&gt;Further Reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://craigmod.com/essays/membership_programs/?utm_medium=email&amp;amp;utm_campaign=Roden%20035%20%20Membership%20Programs%20Year%20Two&amp;amp;utm_content=Roden%20035%20%20Membership%20Programs%20Year%20Two+CID_5867f133bbd6ee19459686d9adb27687&amp;amp;utm_source=mailbot2000&amp;amp;utm_term=Running%20a%20Paid%20Membership%20Program&quot;&gt;Running a Paid Membership Program — by Craig Mod&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;As of year one, I am sad to report: I cannot yet retire or purchase a yacht. I am delighted, however, to report that the &lt;em&gt;Explorers Club&lt;/em&gt; covers my base costs of living. I live fairly simply so these costs are perhaps lower than yours. That said, I don’t live like a hermit, have a comfortable studio / home, big enough to frequently host other artists and writers, and like to cook with fancy butter.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Hypha Worker Co-operative</name></author><summary type="html">The “journalist as entrepreneur” is the latest way for journalists to go “indie”, i.e. monetizing their work not through a publisher but directly through a paying audience. This move has become increasingly easy through plattforms such as Patreon, Memberfull or newsletter plattforms such as Substack and Revue. Though, as noted in [[Influencer—Journalists]] this move has the possibility of compromising the image and credibility of journalists. A form of entrepreneurial journalism is also the emergence of [[New Local Media]]. Small local outlets build often involving minimal overhead, small teams and a focus on digital media. Open Questions Further Reading Running a Paid Membership Program — by Craig Mod As of year one, I am sad to report: I cannot yet retire or purchase a yacht. I am delighted, however, to report that the Explorers Club covers my base costs of living. I live fairly simply so these costs are perhaps lower than yours. That said, I don’t live like a hermit, have a comfortable studio / home, big enough to frequently host other artists and writers, and like to cook with fancy butter.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fractal Society</title><link href="https://digitalgarden.hypha.coop/fractal-society" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fractal Society" /><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-07-26T14:06:29+02:00</updated><id>https://digitalgarden.hypha.coop/Fractal%20Society</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://digitalgarden.hypha.coop/fractal-society"></content><author><name>Hypha Worker Co-operative</name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Emerging Practices</title><link href="https://digitalgarden.hypha.coop/emerging-practices" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Emerging Practices" /><published>2021-07-22T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-07-26T15:31:55+02:00</updated><id>https://digitalgarden.hypha.coop/Emerging%20Practices</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://digitalgarden.hypha.coop/emerging-practices">&lt;p&gt;It‘s been a long-held belief of mine, that journalism doesn‘t have to mean media in the traditional sense. Everyone with access to publishing tools can act like a journalist — i.e. reporting and contextualizing observations and data — but not everyone feels beholden to ethical guidelines, the journalistic ethos of the traditional business model of journalism. Furthermore, the digital present is changing the role of traditional journalists as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More and more we can see hybrid roles emerging, which mix journalism with design, coding, project management or even more exotic skills. Opening up the field of journalism to those experiences might open up a new way of defining the practice itself. Journalism after journalists and journalists after journalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;examples&quot;&gt;Examples&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;internal-link&quot; href=&quot;/influencer-journalists&quot;&gt;Influencer—Journalists&lt;/a&gt; — With a big following on social media becoming not only a prerequesite for journalists but also a way to go indie, the line between journalist, creator and influencers are more and more blurred&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;internal-link&quot; href=&quot;/indie-journalism&quot;&gt;Indie-Journalism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;internal-link&quot; href=&quot;/climate-reporting&quot;&gt;Climate Reporting&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Hypha Worker Co-operative</name></author><summary type="html">It‘s been a long-held belief of mine, that journalism doesn‘t have to mean media in the traditional sense. Everyone with access to publishing tools can act like a journalist — i.e. reporting and contextualizing observations and data — but not everyone feels beholden to ethical guidelines, the journalistic ethos of the traditional business model of journalism. Furthermore, the digital present is changing the role of traditional journalists as well. More and more we can see hybrid roles emerging, which mix journalism with design, coding, project management or even more exotic skills. Opening up the field of journalism to those experiences might open up a new way of defining the practice itself. Journalism after journalists and journalists after journalism. Examples [[Influencer—Journalists]] — With a big following on social media becoming not only a prerequesite for journalists but also a way to go indie, the line between journalist, creator and influencers are more and more blurred [[Indie-Journalism]] [[Climate Reporting]]</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Algorithm</title><link href="https://digitalgarden.hypha.coop/the-algorithm" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Algorithm" /><published>2021-07-22T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-07-26T14:59:16+02:00</updated><id>https://digitalgarden.hypha.coop/The%20Algorithm</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://digitalgarden.hypha.coop/the-algorithm"></content><author><name>Hypha Worker Co-operative</name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry></feed>